{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "Blackbeard died on this state’s island of Ocracoke. Virginia Dare’s birth on an island in this state made her the first person of English descent born in the Americas. A carving of the word “Croatoan” was found on an island in this state’s Outer Banks that was home to a “Lost Colony.” Roanoke was found in, for ten points, what state whose capital was named after Sir Walter Raleigh?",
      "answer": "North Carolina"
    },
    {
      "question": "One of these conflicts effectively ended with the capture of the Taku Forts. A letter that said, “Let us ask, where is your conscience?” was sent to the victorious monarch of these wars. One of these wars began when officials boarded and searched the Arrow. In the first of the Unequal Treaties, Hong Kong was ceded to the winner of these wars as part of the Treaty of Nanking. For ten points, name these 19th century wars in China over a British poppy export.",
      "answer": "Opium Wars"
    },
    {
      "question": "This country is the setting of a novel in which a promise to watch Pinocchio is broken when Jalil refuses to see his estranged daughter. In a story set in this country, Rasheed is angered when his wife Miriam asks what a communist is at the start of a revolution against Daoud Khan. This setting of A Thousand Splendid Suns serves as Amir’s home in one novel before he was forced to flee from a Soviet invasion. For ten points, name this country where Khaled Hosseini’s The Kite Runner is set in Kabul.",
      "answer": "Afghanistan"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man’s sister Sophia once cut a hole in his throne to whisper advice during meetings. Until the death of his half-brother, this man jointly ruled with Ivan V. This man learned shipbuilding in the Netherlands during his “Grand Embassy” tour of Europe. Modernizations under this man included the creation of a new capital on the Neva river. For ten points, identify this “Great” Russian tsar who westernized the country.",
      "answer": [
        "Peter the Great or Peter I",
        "Peter alone after “Great” is read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "One of these events that mainly affected Monterey and Santa Cruz Counties in 1989 temporarily cut off coverage of the World Series and began near Loma Prieta Peak. The Mission District burned in a fire that occurred after one of these events that destroyed the original flag used in the Bear Flag Revolt; that event was centered near the Golden Gate. For ten points, name these type of natural disaster that largely destroyed San Francisco in 1906.",
      "answer": "earthquakes"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Aboriginal activist William Cooper protested this event by giving a petition to a consulate in Melbourne. Herschel Grynszpan’s assassination of the diplomat Ernst von Rath sparked this event, which included the burning of hundreds of buildings, including the Fasanenstrasse Synagogue. For ten points, name this 1938 pogrom in Germany whose name translates to “Night of Broken Glass.”",
      "answer": [
        "Kristallnacht",
        "Night of Broken Glass before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A brand of these products temporarily stopped using green in its packaging during World War II, supposedly to save copper. Leo Burnett designed a mascot for a company that sold these products in an effort to transition away from feminine ad campaigns; that mascot was a cowboy portrayed by several men who later died of COPD and other respiratory diseases. In 1970, the government banned television advertising for, for ten points, what cancer-causing product sold by Lucky Strike and Marlboro?",
      "answer": [
        "cigarettes",
        "answers related to tobacco"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In the final scene of this work, a blindfolded child waves a miniature American flag and the title character reads the inscription “Who cannot live with honor must die with honor” on a knife. This work’s most famous aria, “Un bel di vedremo,” describes the hope of seeing a puff of smoke on the horizon signaling the return of Lieutenant Pinkerton. For ten points, name this opera by Giacomo Puccini whose title character, Cio-Cio San, lives in early 20th century Japan.",
      "answer": "Madame Butterfly or Madama Butterfly"
    },
    {
      "question": "This one-time head of the “Radical Division” organized COINTELPRO to spy on suspected communists, using the program to harass Martin Luther King. Associates of this man included secretary Helen Gandy, who burned his “personal file” after his death, and his deputy Clyde Tolson. The arrests of Machine Gun Kelly and “Public Enemy Number One” John Dillinger were coordinated by a group led by, for ten points, what influential first director of the FBI?",
      "answer": "John Edgar Hoover"
    },
    {
      "question": "A villa in Florence inspired the name of a map of this island known as the Castello Plan. Seyseys, the leader of the Canarsee, led a negotiation for this island. An artillery section built along the southern portion of this island was known as the Battery. Members of the Lenape tribe were supposedly given 60 guilders by Peter Minuit to transfer ownership of this island to the Dutch. For ten points, name this island of New York City that is home to Wall Street.",
      "answer": "Manhattan"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this election year, Governor Scott Walker survived a recall election and Tammy Baldwin was elected as the first openly LGBT Senator in US history. A remark that “there are 47 percent of Americans who will vote for the President no matter what” hurt the Republican Presidential challenger in this election year, who ran on a ticket with Paul Ryan. For ten points, name this year in which Mitt Romney ran against Barack Obama, who won a second term as President.",
        "answer": "2012"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Scott Walker, Tammy Baldwin, and Paul Ryan all served as politicians from this state. Michigan, Pennsylvania, and this state had a margin of victory under 1% in favor of Donald Trump in 2016.",
        "answer": "Wisconsin"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This event’s leader stumbled upon Pompey’s Pillar, where his etched signature remains to this day. Fort Mandan was constructed by participants of this event, who included a slave named York. After setting out from St. Louis, this event’s leaders were joined by Toussaint Charbonneau and his Shoshone wife, Sacagawea. For ten points, name this early 19th century expedition that Thomas Jefferson deployed to scout the Louisiana territory.",
        "answer": [
          "Lewis and Clark Expedition",
          "Corps of Discovery"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Much of the expedition took place along this river, which flows from Montana to the Mississippi River near St. Louis.",
        "answer": "Missouri River"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This god will bring an end to the Kali Yuga in the form of his avatar Kalki. This figure is usually depicted, as in the ancient Padmanabhaswamy [pahd-mah-nah-bah-swah-me] Temple in Kerala, as holding a lotus flower, a mace, and a conch, with blue skin and four arms. One avatar of this God chased a golden deer and married Sita, and was named Rama. For ten points, name this Hindu Preserver god who makes up the Trimurti along with Brahma and Shiva.",
        "answer": "Vishnu"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This avatar of Vishnu is the main speaker of the Bhagavad Gita. A modern sect venerates this avatar with an mantra chanting “Hare [ha-ray] [this figure].”",
        "answer": [
          "Krishna",
          "Hare Krishna"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "After this city fell to France, Napoleon ordered the destruction of the Bucentaur, a ship that was used by this city’s leader each Ascension Day to perform the “Marriage of the Sea” ceremony. This city maintained the fortress city of Famagusta on its island colony of Cyprus. A maritime empire in the Adriatic was ruled by, for ten points, what Italian city-state that is famed for its canals?",
        "answer": "The Most Serene Republic of Venice"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In the original tradition of the Marriage of the Sea ceremony, the holder of this position dropped a ring into the water. The name of this position is related to the English term “duke.”",
        "answer": "Doge of Venice"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Alberto Granado and this man were given a raft to sail on the Amazon River after treating lepers. This man supported Jacobo Arbenz, but when his wife Hilda Gadea was arrested, he moved to Mexico. This man journeyed for nine months on a motorcycle across South America. This revolutionary fought in a revolution that deposed Fulgencio Batista after sailing on the Granma. For ten points, name this Argentine Marxist revolutionary who helped Fidel Castro in Cuba.",
        "answer": "Ernesto “Che” Guevara"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Che supported Jacobo Arbenz in this Central American country. Like Panama City and Mexico City, this country’s capital city shares the name of the country.",
        "answer": "Guatemala City"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This philosopher identified the lowest-level, indivisible units of substance as “monads.” This thinker formulated a principle of “pre-established harmony” in his Discourse on Metaphysics, and he codified the “principle of sufficient reason” in a 1710 work whose title coined the term “theodicy.” The inspiration for Pangloss in Voltaire’s Candide was, for ten points, what German thinker who concluded that ours is the best of all possible worlds?",
        "answer": "Gottfried Wilhelm von Leibniz"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Leibniz’s non-philosophical work included the development of this mathematical field contemporaneously with, and independently of, Isaac Newton.",
        "answer": "calculus"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This group formed after the passing of the Adjusted Compensation Act and had the support of Smedley Butler. Walter Waters led this group, whose members camped on the Anacostia Flats after they were forced to wait until 1945 to redeem certificates for cash. Douglas MacArthur led federal troops to break up, for ten points, what group of disgruntled World War I veterans who marched on Washington D.C. in 1932?",
        "answer": "Bonus Army"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The day after the Bonus Army was dispersed, marcher Joe Angelo met with this US general, whose life Angelo had saved during World War I. This man, nicknamed “Old Blood and Guts,” refused to change his mind and help the marchers.",
        "answer": "George S. Patton"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This structure caused stations on the U6 and U8 to become known as ghost stops. Lucius Clay was appointed as an ambassador after the construction of this structure, and Egon Krenz oversaw its destruction. This structure, which was designed to prevent brain drain, included heavy military presence at locations like Checkpoint Charlie. For ten points, name this barrier that divided the modern capital of Germany during much of the Cold War.",
        "answer": "Berlin Wall"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Berlin Wall was opened in November of this year, one year before Germany was reunified and two years before the Soviet Union officially dissolved.",
        "answer": "1989"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "1920s",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Woman who flew across the Atlantic in 1928 and disappeared in 1937.",
          "answer": "Amelia Earhart"
        },
        {
          "question": "13 year ban on alcohol established by the 18th Amendment and overturned by the 21st Amendment.",
          "answer": "Prohibition"
        },
        {
          "question": "Trial in Tennessee in which a teacher was prosecuted for teaching evolution.",
          "answer": [
            "Scopes Monkey Trial",
            "The State of Tennessee v. John Thomas Scopes"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Organization proposed in Woodrow Wilson’s 14 points, the predecessor to the United Nations.",
          "answer": "League of Nations"
        },
        {
          "question": "Color that names the Tuesday and Thursday which started and ended the stock market crash that began the Great Depression.",
          "answer": [
            "Black",
            "Black Tuesday and/or Black Thursday"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "System used by a namesake Emergency Act in 1921 to limit immigration via the National Origins Formula.",
          "answer": [
            "quota",
            "Emergency Quota Act"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Attorney General whose namesake raids targeted radicals during the first Red Scare.",
          "answer": "Alexander Mitchel Palmer"
        },
        {
          "question": "1928 Pact which resolved not to use war to resolve “disputes or conflicts of whatever nature.”",
          "answer": [
            "Kellogg-Briand Pact",
            "General Treaty for Renunciation of War as an Instrument of National Policy",
            "Pact of Paris"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Henry VIII",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Royal English house to which Henry belonged.",
          "answer": "House of Tudor"
        },
        {
          "question": "Number of women Henry married during his life.",
          "answer": "six"
        },
        {
          "question": "First wife of Henry VIII, the daughter of Ferdinand and Isabella.",
          "answer": "Catherine of Aragon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Church that Henry founded after the pope would not grant him an annulment to that wife.",
          "answer": "Anglican Church or Church of England"
        },
        {
          "question": "Wife who gave birth to Henry’s son Edward VI.",
          "answer": "Jane Seymour"
        },
        {
          "question": "Last woman to marry Henry VIII.",
          "answer": "Catherine Parr"
        },
        {
          "question": "1536 uprising led by Robert Aske in protest of Henry VIII’s anti-Catholic policies.",
          "answer": "Pilgrimage of Grace"
        },
        {
          "question": "War fought during Henry’s reign with the aim of securing his son’s marriage to Mary, Queen of Scots.",
          "answer": "War of the Rough Wooing"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Brazil",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "European country that colonized Brazil, and whose language is Brazil’s official language.",
          "answer": [
            "Portugal",
            "Portuguese"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Site of the 2016 Summer Olympics, the second largest Brazilian city after Sao Paulo.",
          "answer": "Rio de Janeiro"
        },
        {
          "question": "Beverage whose industry dominated the 19th century Brazilian economy, often paired with milk in historical studies.",
          "answer": [
            "coffee",
            "coffee with milk",
            "caf’e com leite"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Country that opposed Brazil, Argentina, and Uruguay in the War of the Triple Alliance.",
          "answer": "Paraguay"
        },
        {
          "question": "Practice that was abolished in Brazil by the 1888 Golden Law.",
          "answer": "slavery"
        },
        {
          "question": "Emperor of Brazil whose daughter Isabel signed the Golden Law while serving as regent.",
          "answer": "Dom Pedro II"
        },
        {
          "question": "President from 1956 to 1961 who built the new capital at Brasilia.",
          "answer": "Juscelino Kubitschek de Oliveira"
        },
        {
          "question": "River where, in 1822, the “cry” of Brazilian independence was made.",
          "answer": [
            "Ipiranga Brook",
            "Cry of Ipiranga"
          ]
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this war, French forces captured enemy plans during the Mechelen Incident. During this conflict, the French navy was destroyed at the Battle of Mers el-Kebir to (20 pts)",
        "prevent it from falling into enemy hands. The initial French plan for this conflict involved rushing to the River Dyle to fight with Belgium. After an attack through the Ardennes circumvented the (10 pts)",
        "Maginot Line in this conflict, French troops were encircled at Dunkirk. For ten points, name this war in which France was conquered by Nazi Germany."
      ],
      "answer": "World War II"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This figure hired a group of men all named Elmer so that when he called for them, they would all show up. This man was said to have drilled holes in maple trees with two huge mosquitoes he had caught. This man owned a cow named (20 pts)",
        "Lucy, as well as an animal that he found freezing in the snow that turned a certain color when exposed to his fireplace. This owner of (10 pts)",
        "Babe the Blue Ox was said to have created the Grand Canyon while dragging his axe behind him. For ten points, name this giant lumberjack of American folklore."
      ],
      "answer": "Paul Bunyan"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This empire made its conquered lands part of the Twelve Doors. In an epic from this empire, a leader wounded an enemy with an arrow with the spur of a (20 pts)",
        "rooster. The Kouroukan Fouga constitution and the Gbara assembly were central to this empire, whose founder defeated Sumanguru at the Battle of Kirina. (10 pts)",
        "Sundiata Keita founded this empire, which controlled trans-Sahara trade. For ten points, name this empire that devalued gold after its ruler Mansa Musa went on a hajj in 1324."
      ],
      "answer": "Mali Empire"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A man born in this city posed a problem about the growth rate of a rabbit population in his book Liber Abaci. A value approximating the Golden Ratio can be found by dividing two successive terms in a sequence named for that man born in this city, (20 pts)",
        "Fibonacci. Vincenzo Vivani claims that De Motu’s central idea, that objects of different masses have the same (10 pts)",
        "acceleration, was verified by a man’s experiment in this city. For ten points, name this Italian city, where balls were allegedly dropped by Galileo from its namesake leaning tower."
      ],
      "answer": "Pisa"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Alexander Gardner’s “Sketchbook of the War” focuses on this conflict, during which James Gibson took an iconic photograph of a hospital at Savage Station. Another photographer, Timothy O’Sullivan, showed the corpses at one of this war’s decisive battles in “The (20 pts)",
        "Harvest of Death.” Over $100,000 was spent on photographic efforts during this war by a man who popularized the daguerreotype technique in (10 pts)",
        "America. Mathew Brady was a prominent photographer during, for ten points, what war which was the subject of pictures like The Dead at Antietam?"
      ],
      "answer": "American Civil War"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) African-American soldier William Williams was one of four men killed during an attack on this fort carried out by Alexander Cochrane. This fort held an object created by Mary Pickersgill that inspired a poem later (20 pts)",
        "set to the tune “To Anacreon in Heaven;” that poem was written by a lawyer visiting (10 pts)",
        "Baltimore who observed an attack on this fort in 1814. For ten points, name this fort whose defense inspired Francis Scott Key to write the words of “The Star-Spangled Banner.”"
      ],
      "answer": "Fort McHenry"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The death of a leader in this location led power to shift to the Flensburg government under Karl Donitz. Hans Krebs shot himself in the head as troops closed in on this location, located under the (20 pts)",
        "Chancellery building. This location was the last of its function, preceding the Eagle’s Nest and (10 pts)",
        "Wolf’s Lair. The most famous occupant of this location took cyanide before having his body burnt. For ten points, name this underground command post where Adolf Hitler committed suicide."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Fuhrerbunker",
        "descriptive answers relating to Adolf Hitler’s bunker in Berlin"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A ruler with this first name supposedly forged a letter from his mother Emma in order to lure and capture his step-brother Alfred; that ruler had the nickname “Harefoot” and was the son of Canute the Great. A later ruler with this first name used an army of (20 pts)",
        "huscarls to defeat his brother Tostig at the Battle of Stamford Bridge, but was killed by an (10 pts)",
        "arrow to his eye less than a month later. For ten points, give this name shared by the Anglo-Saxon king who lost to William the Conqueror at the Battle of Hastings."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Harold",
        "Harold I",
        "Harold Harefoot",
        "Harold Godwinson after “huscarls” is read"
      ]
    }
  ]
}